<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="wlr_attached_surface_unstable_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2025 Bailey Stoner

    Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this
    software and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted
    without fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in
    all copies and that both that copyright notice and this permission
    notice appear in supporting documentation, and that the name of
    the copyright holders not be used in advertising or publicity
    pertaining to distribution of the software without specific,
    written prior permission. The copyright holders make no
    representations about the suitability of this software for any
    purpose. It is provided "as is" without express or implied
    warranty.

    THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS
    SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
    FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN
    AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION,
    ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF
    THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="zwlr_attached_surface_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="create surfaces attached to toplevels">
      This interface allows clients to create surfaces that are attached to
      and positioned relative to an xdg_toplevel window. Unlike subsurfaces,
      attached surfaces can extend beyond the parent window's bounds and are
      rendered independently. Unlike popups, they are not dismissed when
      focus changes.

      This is useful for persistent auxiliary UI such as preview panels,
      toolbars, or inspectors that should appear adjacent to a window.
    </description>

    <request name="get_attached_surface">
      <description summary="create an attached surface">
        Create an attached surface for an existing wl_surface, attaching it
        to the specified xdg_toplevel parent.

        Creating an attached surface from a wl_surface which has a buffer
        attached or committed is a client error, and any attempts by a client
        to attach or manipulate a buffer prior to the first configure event
        must also be treated as errors.

        After creating an attached surface and setting it up, the client must
        perform an initial commit without any buffer attached. The compositor
        will reply with a configure event. The client must acknowledge it and
        is then allowed to attach a buffer to map the surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zwlr_attached_surface_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
      <arg name="parent" type="object" interface="xdg_toplevel"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy the attached surface manager. Attached surfaces created
        through this manager are not affected.
      </description>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="role" value="0" summary="wl_surface has another role"/>
      <entry name="already_constructed" value="1" summary="wl_surface has a buffer attached or committed"/>
      <entry name="invalid_parent" value="2" summary="parent is not an xdg_toplevel"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zwlr_attached_surface_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="attached surface interface">
      An interface for surfaces attached to an xdg_toplevel. These surfaces
      are positioned relative to their parent toplevel and can extend beyond
      the parent's bounds.

      Attached surface state (position, size) is double-buffered and will be
      applied at the time wl_surface.commit of the corresponding wl_surface
      is called.

      Attaching a null buffer to an attached surface unmaps it.
    </description>

    <enum name="anchor">
      <description summary="anchor edge">
        Specifies which edge of the parent window the surface is anchored to.
        When anchored, the compositor automatically positions the surface
        adjacent to that edge, and repositions it when the parent resizes.
      </description>
      <entry name="none" value="0" summary="no anchor, use manual positioning"/>
      <entry name="top" value="1" summary="anchor to top edge"/>
      <entry name="bottom" value="2" summary="anchor to bottom edge"/>
      <entry name="left" value="3" summary="anchor to left edge"/>
      <entry name="right" value="4" summary="anchor to right edge"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="set_anchor">
      <description summary="set anchor edge and margin">
        Set the anchor edge and margin for automatic positioning. When an
        anchor is set, the compositor positions the surface adjacent to
        that edge of the parent window, offset by the margin.

        The offset parameter positions the surface along the anchored edge:
        - For left/right anchors: offset from the top of the parent
        - For top/bottom anchors: offset from the left of the parent

        Setting anchor to "none" disables automatic positioning and the
        surface uses manual set_position coordinates instead.

        Anchor state is double-buffered, see wl_surface.commit.
      </description>
      <arg name="anchor" type="uint" enum="anchor"/>
      <arg name="margin" type="int" summary="gap between parent and surface"/>
      <arg name="offset" type="int" summary="offset along the anchored edge"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_position">
      <description summary="set position relative to parent">
        Set the position of the surface relative to the parent toplevel's
        top-left corner, in surface-local coordinates. The surface can be
        positioned outside the parent's bounds.

        This is only used when anchor is set to "none". When an anchor is
        set, the compositor calculates position automatically.

        Position is double-buffered, see wl_surface.commit.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="int"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_size">
      <description summary="set the size of the surface">
        Set the size of the surface in surface-local coordinates.

        Size is double-buffered, see wl_surface.commit.
      </description>
      <arg name="width" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="height" type="uint"/>
    </request>

    <request name="ack_configure">
      <description summary="ack a configure event">
        When a configure event is received, if a client commits the surface
        in response to the configure event, then the client must make an
        ack_configure request sometime before the commit request, passing
        along the serial of the configure event.

        A client is not required to commit immediately after sending an
        ack_configure request - it may even ack_configure several times
        before its next surface commit.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="the serial from the configure event"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the attached surface">
        Destroy the attached surface.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="configure">
      <description summary="suggest a surface change">
        The configure event asks the client to resize its surface.

        Clients should arrange their surface for the new size, and then send
        an ack_configure request with the serial sent in this configure event
        before committing the new surface.

        The width and height arguments specify the size of the surface in
        surface-local coordinates.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="width" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="height" type="uint"/>
    </event>

    <event name="closed">
      <description summary="surface should be closed">
        The closed event is sent by the compositor when the surface will no
        longer be shown. This happens when the parent toplevel is destroyed.
        The client should destroy the attached surface after receiving this
        event.
      </description>
    </event>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="invalid_size" value="0" summary="size is invalid"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>
</protocol>
